Guide to the Archives of Irish America Material Culture and Ephemera Collection AIA.041
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Material Culture and Ephemera Collection
1888-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.041
14.21 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes, 4 oversized flat boxes, 1 custom box, 3 record cartons, and 2 folders in shared housing
The Archives of Irish America (AIA) Material Culture and Ephemera Collection is an artificial collection composed of objects individually donated or found in other AIA collections. The collection consists of various items such as buttons, bumper stickers, hats, tickets, membership cards, pens, pins, musical instruments, and t-shirts -- many of which relate to Irish and Irish American organizations.
Arrangement
Items are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of various items such as buttons, bumper stickers, hats, tickets, membership cards, pens, pins, musical instruments, and t-shirts -- many of which relate to Irish and Irish American organizations. Contents of the collection came in as individual accessions or as part of larger accessions, including the Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Irish Memories Collection, and were organized together into this artificial collection.
Historical Note
The Archives of Irish America Material Culture and Ephemera Collection compliments the entire Archives of Irish America because its contents provide information on many topics and individuals not formally represented in the other collections. The unique format of many of the materials - hats, t-shirts, bumper stickers - provide insight to scholars and researchers in the methods used to convey information within the Irish American community.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was created via active collection by staff, contributions from donors, and from material removed from other AIA collections. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.023, 2012.037, and 2019.114.
Custodial History
Items in the Archives of Irish America Material Culture and Ephemera Collection were donated, purchased, or found in other AIA collections.
In March 2025, Marion Casey donated an accretion of drawings, postcards, and an autograph book; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.028.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Footballs (balls for sports).; Hats.; Memorabilia.; Cigar boxes.; Plaques (flat objects); T-shirts; Bumper stickers.; Stationery.; Irish Americans.; Passports.; Musical instruments.
- Annie Ryan Postcards and Autograph Book, 1888-1893 (Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 9)
- Armband: "Formation", undated (Box 2, Object 6)
- Armbands: "Frank Stagg, RIP" (IRA hunger strike), circa 1970s (Box 2, Object 5)
- Ashtray: "Ireland" / Made in the Republic of Ireland by N.B.C. Ltd., undated (Box 4, Object 3)
- Audio Reel: St. Patrick's Day, 1980 (Box Shared Tamiment 012, Quarter inch audio reel 041_0001)
- Badges, Name Tags, & Ribbons, 1945-1992 (Box 3, Object 4)
- Banner: Brehon Law Society, undated (Box 8)
- Banner: Irish American Heritage Committee of the New York City Department of Education (Box 14)
- Baseball cap with image of Irish flag, undated (Box 1, Object 5)
- Baseball cap with "N.Y. State Convention A.O.H. Niagra Falls 1987 Albany, N.Y. in '89" Silkscreen, 1989 (Box 1, Object 6)
- Bookmark: "An Olde Irish Toast", undated (Box 2, Object 8)
- Bookmark with copper pence: Bank of Ireland, undated (Box 3, Object 12)
- Bumper Sticker: "The Irish Will Remember in November", undated (Box 2, Object 3)
  Memorabilia.; Hats.
- Bumper Sticker: "Save the Leprechaun", undated (Box 3, Object 14)
- Bumper Sticker: "Strip Search the Queen", undated (Box 3, Object 15)
- Bumper sticker: "There's every reason to buy Irish", undated (Box 2, Object 3)
- Button Accordion and Case, undated; cuid36506 (Box 15)
  Scope and Contents
  The button accordion and case came with two tags, one of which had the logo for the Museum of the City of the New York and Adrian Flannelly's address. The second tag reads, "Ireland America the Ties That Bind" Music Vitrine "Micky Carton" button accordion case. Ireland America the Ties That Bind was a 2011 exhibition presented by the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, in collaboration with New York University's Glucksman Ireland House, the Irish Film Institute, and Culture Ireland. The exhibition was curated by Professor Marion R. Casey from Glucksman Ireland House. This accordion was featured in this exhibition.
- Buttons and Pins, undated (Box 3, Object 3)
- Calendar (magnet): Kathleen's of Donegal Irish Imports, 1998 (Box 3, Object 13)
- Calendar: shape of shamrock, undated (Box 3, Object 6)
- Cigar Box: "Irish Molly O", undated (Box 4, Object 2)
- Cigarette Card: Frank Riley, Irish American Athletic Club (member of 1908 American Olympic Team), undated
- Coasters (4): Harp, Guinness, Bank of Ireland, undated, 1998 (Box 2, Object 7)
- Concertina, undated (Box 11)
- Concertina Manual, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 4)
- Derry Sash, 2011 (Box Shared Tamiment 163)
- Documents, 1962, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 5)
- Flags: U.S.A. and Republic of Ireland (small), undated (Box 7)
- Game Passes, Polo Grounds: Gaelic Games, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Object 2)
- Guinness Mug, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 163)
- Handkerchief with embroidered green flower, undated (Box 7)
- Hurling Ball, leather, undated (Box 4, Object 1)
- John Malone Drawings, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 187, Folder 22)
- Keychain: Irish Voice (Box 3, Object 5)
- Lottery tickets: Irish Hospitals' Sweepstakes (John J. Cudahy), Oct 1985 (Box 3, Object 10)
- Michael Flannery Memorial Magazine, 2001 (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 2)
- Moore Centenary Association of Newark, New Jersey, 1879-05-28 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 21)
- Mouse pad: Irish Echo, undated (Box 1, Object 7)
- New York World's Fair Booklet, 1939 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 22)
- Paperweight: "Moynihan for Senate", undated (Box 3, Object 7)
- Passport - Martin Connolly, 1940 (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 3)
- Plaque: "An Old Irish Benediction", undated (Box 1, Object 2)
- Plaque: County Clare P.B. & S. Association; to Michael Mahoney, undated (Box 2, Object 11)
- Plaque: "Ireland Unfree Shall Never Be At Peace - 1916 - Patrick Pearse", undated (Box 5, Object 3)
- Plaque: Irish American Cultural Institute, "The Irish Way Program", 1981 (Box 5, Object 2)
- Plaque: "Irish American Heritage Museum Charter Member", undated (Box 2, Object 4)
- Photo on wood block: Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, undated (Box 3, Object 1)
- Pocket-Size Songbook No. 3, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 6-7)
- Quilted Runner, undated (Box 9, Object 1)
- Record Album: "The Irish Uprising, 1916-1922", undated (Box 5, Object 1)
- Recorder, undated (Box 9, Object 6)
- Ribbon: Irish American Athletic Association Member: " Nothing too Good for the Irish-Americans" Banquet, 30 Oct 1911 (Box 2, Object 10)
- Rosary, undated (Box 3, Object 5)
- Ruler: Bank of Ireland, undated (Box 3, Object 11)
- Scally cap with "Hibernians/Budweiser" Patch, undated (Box 1, Object 3)
- Stamp: Bank of Ireland, Deposits, undated (Box 3, Object 8)
- Stamp: Doran Film Distribution: U.S. Distribution and Sales; wood and rubber, undated (Box 3, Object 9)
- Stationery pad: Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians, undated (Box 1, Object 4)
- Stationery Sets (3): Aer Lingus 1st Class, undated (Box 2, Object 1)
- Shoelaces with shamrocks, undated (Box 2, Object 9)
- T-Shirt: 22nd Annual Washington Irish Folk Festival, Montgomery County Fairgrounds [MD}, Sep 5 1998-Sep 6 1998 (Box 6, Object 10)
- T-Shirt: Ceol Nua '79, undated (Box 9, Object 2)
- T-Shirt: "Conradh na Gailge – Craobh Baile Phit", undated (Box 6, Object 1)
- T-Shirt: Coogan Salsa Blues and Shamrocks, NYC "Remember Captain Frederick Ill, FDNY, Mar 2, 2003 (Box 6, Object 11)
- T-Shirt: "Free Jim Barr – Irish Political Prisoner in America", undated (Box 6, Object 2)
- T-Shirt: "The Great Hunger", undated (Box 6, Object 3)
- T-Shirt: Ireland Worldcup 1994 (Box 6, Object 4)
- T-Shirt: "Irish Emigrant Vote Campaign, ©IEVC '91", 1991 (Box 6, Object 5)
- T-Shirt: "Republic of Ireland, World Cup '94", 1994 (Box 6, Object 6)
- T-Shirt: "Riverdance", 1995-2000 (Box 9, Object 3)
- T-Shirt: "Scannān '92: A Festival of Modern Irish Film", 1992 (Box 6, Object 7)
- T-Shirt: St. Patrick's Day Budweiser, undated (Box 9, Object 4)
- T-Shirt: The Starry Plough Symbol of Irish Freedom, undated (Box 9, Object 5)
- T-Shirt: "Support Irish Political Prisoners • H-Block and Armagh Comm.", undated (Box 6, Object 8)
- T-Shirt: "Ulysses S. Grant and the Irish" - Wildgeese.com, undated (Box 6, Object 9)
- Tea Towel: "County Roscomman" (linen) (Box 7)
- Tea Towel: "Famous Irish Americans" (linen/cotton) (Box 7)
- Umbrella, undated (Box 10)